Guide to the John Emory Bryant Papers, 1851-1955 and undated RL.00167
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Writings, Journals, Scrapbooks, 1853-1950s; 3
  - Writings, 1868-1886 (Box 15)
    Includes meeting minutes, fragment of handwritten copy Georgia constitution of 1868 regarding voting rights, "Resolution calling on Supreme Court for decision on question of eligibility of colored men," "Names of those who pledge to defeat Foster Blodgett in General Assembly, Georgia, 1868," fragment of resolution passed in 1869, list of subscribers for The Southern Advance Association 1885, Republican appointment announcements, and election statistics.
  - Writings, 1870-1874 (Box 16)
    Includes fragment reporting on Democratic convention in which labor laws were discussed. The fragment ends by saying, "Your memoriolist therefore feel warrented in saying that the evident object of the Governor in refusing to organize and arm companies composed of colored men is to enable our former masters the more easily to control our labor." Also includes, "Plan for managing the Macon convention, May 8, 1892," minutes from the Senate Judiciary Committee, Washington, February 12, 1870, regarding Governor Bullock, and "Speech Delivered in McEntire Hall, Savannah, Georgia, August 20th." This speech was given "in reply to charges made against the Honorable John E. Bryant by Honorable T. G. Campbell previous to his nomination to Congress." T.G. Campbell could be Tunis Campbell.
  - Writings, 1872-1874 (Box 16)
    Mainly documents related to Bryant's run for Congress in 1874. Including a document concerning voting laws addressed to JEB, 1872; notification by JEB of contested election for the first congressional district of Georgia, 1874; document supporting Bryant as the nominee for Congress; testimony of Stanley Young, Supervisor of Elections at Waynesboro Georgia; precinct voting statistics; voting demographics for Georgia; fragment describing election fraud.
  - Writings, 1873-1875 (Box 16)
    Includes brief biography of J. G. Clarke, list of speeches given by defenders of slavery, racism, and the Confederacy, report of speech given by Captain William Hughes to the Confederate Survivors' Association, proceeding of the Southern Historical Society at Richmond, Virginia, October 1873, including an address by General Wade Hampton, and the University of Virginia Anniversary Oration of General John S. Preston, Charlottesville, July 1, 1875.
  - Writings, 1873-1884 (Box 16)
    Includes Southern Advance Association appeals for aid, clippings about the Southern Historical Society including ideas about the "two peoples" of the North and the South, clipping about Alexander H. Stephens "Corner Stone" speech in support of slavery and White supremacy, summary of remarks made by Reverend Dr. Palmer about the "lost cause" and the principles for which the Confederacy fought.
  - Writings, 1874-1899 (Box 16)
    Includes miscellaneous notes about Puritans, short essays entitled "God's Providence," "America," "Anxious Thoughts," "The Armada." The essays and notes are written on the back of letter head, some of which is addressed to Rev. Julius Zeller. Also includes "Death of Mrs. Judson."
  - Writings, 1875-1880 (Box 16)
    Includes report of Benjamin H. Hill's speech in Athens, May 8th 1875, meeting notes "of the Committee appointed to consider the Southern questions, as presented by Col. J. E. Bryant," Providence, Rhode Island, 1879, "Laboring Mans Association of Burke County [Georgia]" founding document, "The Southern Advance Association. The South. The Condition. The Cause. The remedy," [1880], "The Anti-Bourbon Movement," [1880], "The Southern Advance Association. It's History," [1880].
  - Emma Bryant's diary, 1876 (Box 16)
    Includes day-to-day notes about church attendance, reading, sewing, health and illness, letter writing, missing her husband. There is some mention of drawing and painting.
  - Methodist Episcopal Church, 1878-1883 (Box 16)
    Includes notes from the Georgia conference November 27th, 1884, clippings about the church and the divisions based on slavery, "Our White Work in Georgia and Alabama" clipping, "Dr. Fuller's position, Atlanta, Georgia, March 23, 1883: Equal Rights to both races. Each race must rise largely by it's own efforts," "Organization of Holston Conference," "Schools among the destitute whites at the South: The schools in North Carolina, our school at Atlanta," notes from a missionary meeting in New York, 1883, resolutions made at the educational convention, June 20th, 1883, list of money raised for schools in southern states, and demographics of black and white members of M.E. church in Georgia.
  - Writings, 1880-1883 (Box 16)
    Includes "Address to the People by a Committee of the National Union League on the Political Situation of the Country," 1883, "The Southern Question: the Conflict between the two civilizations," draft of speech about the "Bourbon element" in the Democratic party, "The Two Civilizations: the conflict between them not ended," "The Education of the Middle Class at the South," description of the National Union Association [1880].
  - Methodist Episcopal Church, 1880-1886 (Box 16)
    Includes "The South. The Opportunities for Christian Work," [1880], documents supporting the Southern Advance Association, report about the revival work of the Marietta Street Methodist Episcopal Church at Atlanta, Georgia, [1886], presentation to the Woman's Home Missionary Society, Baltimore Conference, on the "Home missionary work among the illiterate and destitute white people at the South," 1886, clipping from the Boston Watchman on "The Intentions of the Southern Bourbon Leaders," 1886.
  - Writings, 1884-1885 (Box 16)
    Includes Southern Advance Association list of subscribers, draft of speech addressing the Republicans of Georgia regarding a defamatory pamphlet targeting Bryant.
  - Address at Grant Memorial University, 1886 (Box 16)
  - Methodist Episcopal Church, 1886-1889 and undated (Box 16)
    Includes "Missionary work among the destitute whites of Atlanta," "Our White work in the Southern States," and other writings and clippings about Bryant's views on white working-class southerners.
  - Writings, 1888 (Box 17)
    Includes "The Southern Problem" and other rebuttals and criticisms of the Southern Historical Society and education in the South
  - Writings, 1892 (Box 17)
    G.A.R. Memorial Day address, Mt. Vernon, N.Y.
  - Autobiography of Alice Bryant Zeller, undated (Box 17)
  - Biographical and genealogical information, 1950 and undated (Box 17)
  - Composition, undated (Box 17)
    Perhaps a draft of a short story written in the 19th century
  - Scrapbook, 1861-1866 (Box 17)
    Includes orders received by Bryant during the Civil War and information regarding the Freedmen's Bureau investigation in 1866
  - Scrapbook, 1868-1874 (Box 17)
    Clippings about Republican politics
  - Scrapbook, 1872-1875 (Box 18)
  - Scrapbook of Alice Bryant, 1892-1894 (Box 18)
    Clippings, programs, some which document Alice Bryant's involvement with the Young Woman's Christian Temperance Union of Westchester County
  - Scrapbook of Julius Zeller, 1892-1893 (Box 18)
    Clippings, programs from events and organizations in Athens, Tennessee
  - Scrapbooks of Alice Bryant, 1893 and undated; 3 folders (Box 18)
    Clippings related to social and church activities in Mount Vernon
  - Real Estate Mount Vernon Suburban Land Company scrapbook, 1890-1893 (Box 19)
  - City of Mount Vernon scrapbook, 1891-1892 (Box 19)
  - New York Politics scrapbook, 1891-1893 (Box 19)
- Printed Materials and Ephemera, 1860s-1906 and undated; 4
  Mostly newspaper clippings regarding Republican politics from 1863-1906. Includes some original and preservation copies of broadsides. Other original broadsides were removed from the collection and individually cataloged. There are five black and white reproduction copies of photographs of the Bryants as well as a book of photographs of Union Army Officers.
  - Senior Union Officers photograph book, 1860s (Box 20)
  - Broadsides, pamphlets, and ephemera, 1865-1899 (Box 20)
  - Preservation copies of broadsides, 1866-1899 (Box 21)
  - Recipes for medicine, 1872 (Box 20)
    Includes 5 remedies for ailments
  - Preservation photocopies of broadsides, pamphlets, speeches, 1866-1895; 2 folders (Box 20)
  - Church documents, 1886-1889 (Box 20)
  - Calling cards, undated (Box 20)
  - Photographs of Bryants (Box 20)
    Reproductions of five photographs
  - U.S. Grant University photograph of professors and students, 1891 (Box 20)
  - Clippings, 1863-1882 (Box 21)
  - Clippings, 1879 April 2 (Box 21)
  - Clippings, 1883 (Box 21)
  - Clippings, 1884-1885 (Box 21)
  - Clippings from The Southern Advance, 1885 December (Box 21)
  - Clippings, 1886 (Box 21)
  - Clippings, 1887-1893 (Box 21)
  - Clippings, 1895-1906 (Box 21)
- William Anderson Pledger, 1874-1889; 5
  William Anderson Pledger (1852-1904) was an editor of the Atlanta Blade, teacher, and prominent Black Republican politician. In 1880 Pledger was elected chairman of the Republican state committee in Georgia, the first Black man to serve in that office. He and Bryant worked together and were political allies. The letter press copybook in this series includes faint copies of letters written by Pledger to various Georgian politicians and Republicans including John Emory Bryant, Henry McNeal Turner, E. R. Belcher, Benjamin Conly, Henry Farrow, M.T. Ackerman, and others. Also included in this series is a typescript of the letter press copybook by Raymond Zeller and a scrapbook created by Pledger about Georgian Republican politics and Black leadership and participation.
  - William A. Pledger letter book typescript, 1875-1879 (Box 22)
    Two typescript copies created by Raymond Zeller. The typescript is incomplete in many places and includes corrections written in pencil.
  - William A. Pledger letter book, 1875-1879; 1 Volumes (Box 22)
    The original letter book is difficult to read due to fading, faint ink. The notes written here were gleaned from the typescript made by Raymond Zeller and should be verified in the letter book if possible. Includes letters written to various politicians and Republicans including John Emory Bryant, Henry McNeal Turner, E. R. Belcher, Benjamin Conley, Henry Farrow, M.T. Ackerman, and others. Many of the letters are about seeking employment from Republicans. Pledger states that "The schools of this county being in the hands of the Democrats and they having such an avowed hatred to me till it is become impossible for me to obtain employment" (page 23). He writes recommendation letters and comes to the defense of others. He makes repeated arguments as to why African-Americans should be appointed to government positions. He also mentions threats against him, the Ku Klux Klan, and his unwillingness to abandon his principles and Republican ideals (page 104 and page 145). Some of his letters attend to the business of the Grand Fountain of Georgia (also referred to as the "colored Good Templars") a Black temperance organization. On page 206 he mentions relations between the White and Black templars of Georgia, and a schism between the American and English orders. In a letter to O. P. Morton, Pledger describes injustices faced by African-Americans in Georgia and argues as to why it is important that the Republican party remain in power (pages 157-163). Pledger writes a letter to the editor critiquing plans for emigration to Liberia, "We were born in America, our fore fathers and mothers for generations back are buried here, and when we leave for another land let us leave as men, not chattel..." (page 213).
  - William A. Pledger scrapbook, 1874-1889; 1 Volumes (Box 22)
    Mainly clippings about Georgian Republican politics and black leadership and participation. Some of the articles mention Pledger's involvement and opinions.
  - William A. Pledger scrapbook (photocopy), 1874-1889 (Box 23)